A Finding Aid to the Carus Gallery Records, 1967-2002, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Carus Gallery records
1967-2002
Archives of American Art
Carus Gallery
AAA.carugall
Archival Resource Key
3.2 Linear feet
The records of Carus Gallery measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1967-2002. This collection documents Dorothea Carus Isserstedt's management of the New York gallery through a small amount of business and personal correspondence; business records regarding acquisitions, sales, and consignments; intentories of artwork and rare books; exhibition catalogs, press clippings, and other printed material; and photographs depicting artwork and exhibition installations.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as 5 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Correspondence, 1974-2000 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Business Records, 1971-1996 (1.8 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Inventories, 1973-2002 (0.6 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1967-1992 (0.6 linear feet; Box 3-4)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1980s-1990s (4 folders; Box 4)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were donated to the Archives in 2004 by Dr. Gheorghe Costinescu and Mrs. Silvelin von Scanzoni Costinescu, the heirs and executors of Dorothy Carus Isserstedt's estate.
Scope and Contents
The records of Carus Gallery measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1967-2002. This collection documents Dorothea Carus Isserstedt's management of the New York gallery through a small amount of business and personal correspondence; business records regarding acquisitions, sales, and consignments; intentories of artwork and rare books; exhibition catalogs, press clippings, and other printed material; and photographs depicting artwork and exhibition installations.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
The Carus Gallery was founded by Dorothea Carus Isserstedt (1914-2002). The gallery's primary interest was in European Graphic Arts, specifically German Expressionism, and Russian Constructivism. The gallery exhibited works by Alexander Archipenko, Ernst Barlach, Max Beckmann, Heinrich Campendonk, Otto Dix, Lyonel Feininger, Natalia Goncharova, George Grosz, Erich Heckel, Alexej Jawlensky, Wassily Kandinsky, Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Paul Klee, Gustav Klimt, Max Klinger, Kathe Kollowitz, El Lissitzky, Kazimir Malevich, László Moholy-Nagy, Marlow Moss, Otto Mueller, Edvard Munch, Emil Nolde, Christian Rohlfs and Egon Schiele.
In 1968, following the death of her parents, Isserstedt opened the Carus Gallery, which was located on the ground level of her home at 243 E 82nd street in New York. The gallery was relocated to Madison Avenue in 1974 and finally to 1044 Madison Avenue where it remained until Isserstedt's retirement in 1996.
Dorothy was born in 1914 in Elberfeld, Germany. She studied art history and archeology at Freiburg University, receiving a doctorate in 1944. Towards the end of World War II Dorothy escaped to East Germany where she settled in Hamburg and found work as a supervisor with the British Forces Network. In 1952 she immigrated to Yorkville, NY where she worked in her father's print and framing shop. Dorothy became an American citizen in 1957.
Expressionism (Art); Constructivism (Art); Art, Modern -- 20th century; Futurism (Art); Photographs; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State); Carus Isserstedt, Dorthea, 1914-2002
- Correspondence, 1972-2000; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is minimal and consist primarily of art inquiries and similar letters to private collectors, conservators, and other galleries, specifically the Prakapas Gallery and the Skulima Galarie. There is also a small amount of correspondence regarding exhibitions and sales.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1988-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence, 1977-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Business Correspondence, Prakapas Gallery, 1974-1976; 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business Correspondence, Skulima Galerie, 1986-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Business Records, 1971-1996; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.8 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Business records include documents detailing acquisitions, sales, and consignments. Also found are financial, legal, and office documents.
  - Aquisitions and Sales, 1987-1990; 1972-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Acquisitions, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sales, 1974-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
  - Invoices, 1971-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14-18)
  - Consignments, 1976-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Pricelists, 1975-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Check Ledger, 1982-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Taxes, 1975-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Phone Log, 1988-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - "Jawlensky Affair" Legal Proceedings, 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Europe, 1977-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Notebooks, 1972-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
- Inventories, 1973-2002; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Inventories include lists of artworks and rare books that could be found at the Carus Gallery. This series also includes a set of index cards containing catalog information regarding artwork.
  - Artworks, 1973-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Rare Artists' Book Sale, 1967-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Artists' Books and Prints, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Index Cards of Gallery Library, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Index Cards of Gallery Library, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Printed Material, 1967-1992; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Printed material includes a number of gallery catalogs, exhibition announcements, and press releases. The series also includes a catalog that was originally bound detailing information regarding the gallery's art holdings; most entries also include a small thumbnail. Additionally, this series contains a limited number of magazine and newspaper clippings.
  - Catalogs, 1975-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Gallery Invitations, 1975-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1980-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Catalog Clippings, A-J, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Catalog Clippings, K-Z, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Printed Artwork, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Carus Gallery Advertisements, 1967-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Press Kit Materials, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Press Releases, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Photographic Material, 1980s-1990s; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 4
  Photographs and slides depict artwork by Felix Del Marle, El Lissitzky, and others. In addition to photographs, this series also contains slides of gallery installations at the Carus Gallery.
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Felix Del Marle, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Artwork, El Lissitzky, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Installation Photographs and Slides, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)